Guide to the Printmaker File [1730]-2014, undated (bulk 1800-1860) PR 58
New-York Historical Society
Printmaker File
[1730]-2014, undated (bulk 1800-1860)
New-York Historical Society
PR 58
6.4 Linear feet (13 boxes, 5 drawers of flat files, 1 drawer of oversize flat files, 1 oversize framed item)
The Printmaker File is comprised of prints which are filed by the artist or engraver. It includes aquatints, engravings, etchings, lithographs, and woodcuts. It includes many scenes and views of New York City. The prints in this collection are likely to be known or studied because of their creators or because of their significance in the history of American printmaking
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection is comprised of gifts from multiple donors, and several purchases.
Access Restrictions
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Scope and Content Note
The Printmaker File spans the period from the 1730s to the present and contains etchings, engravings, aquatints, and lithographs, mainly views of New York City and the east coast of the United States.
Historically, many items acquired by the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections were filed by subject or geographical location. Prints were housed in the Printmaker File if the importance of the artist or printmaker was deemed more important than the subject or place. For example, fine art prints of geographical locations were filed here instead of in the Geographic File. In many cases (i.e. Louis Prang, Bufford's Lithography) there are other prints by printmakers represented here in different collections throughout the Department. This file reflects a historical way of organizing prints, and now creates a backbone for any future filing by printmaker. Note that in 2016, the prints formerly housed in PR 229, Fine Art Prints of New York City, were merged into the Printmaker File.
"Printmaker" generally means the engraver, etcher, or lithographer of a print. In some cases it refers to the publisher of a print or to the original artist. In all cases, any other known names associated with the print (i.e. original artist, sketch designer, publisher) are given here. Lithographs found in this file are generally notable for their early dates. Lithography firms such as Bufford's Lithography and H. N. Sumner & Co. are considered the "printmaker," as is Jacques-Gerard Milbert, who did not actually draw on stone many of the views after his work found in this File.
Many prints collected here are remarkable for their age, their provenance, or their historical significance. Early views of New York City, Savannah, Georgia, and Charlestown, South Carolina can be found in the File. However, there are also a fair amount of twentieth-century prints. Points of local interest -- including various skylines of Manhattan, the Brooklyn Bridge, Central Park, the New York Stock Exchange, the Woolworth Building, and the World Trade Center -- are well-represented.
Important New York artists from throughout the twentieth century are represented in the collection. Artists with four or more prints include: Paul Berdanier, Arthur Cohen, K. Dehman, John Mackie Falconer, Agnes B. Fernbach, Albert Flanagan, Julius F. Gayler, Joseph W. Golinkin, Edward S. Hewitt, F. Leo Hunter, Nat Lowell, William Meyerowitz, Charles F.W. Mielatz, Betty Waldo Parish, Philip Reisman, Shunji Sakuyama, Anton Schutz, T.F. Simon, Emily Trueblood, William H. Wallace, Charles Henry White, Lawrence Nelson Wilbur, and Louis Wolchonok.
In addition, the collection includes small samples of the work of John Taylor Arms, Gottlob Briem, Fritz Eichenberg, Red Grooms, Richard Haas, Childe Hassam, Martin Lewis, James Pennell, Ernest D. Roth, and Richard Sloat.
Women printmakers found here include Isabel Bishop, Edith Bry, Mabel Dwight, Su-Li Hung, Yvonne Jacquette, Wuanita Smith, Caroline Phelps Stokes, and Karen Whitman, in addition to Fernbach, Parish, and Trueblood.
The collection is arranged into three series by size of print, to ensure correct handling and housing of the material: Series I. Prints 16 x 20" and smaller; Series II. Prints 16 x 20" to 30 x 40"; Series III. Prints larger than 30 x 40". Print titles are taken from inscriptions where possible. Titles given in brackets were assigned during processing.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series by size of print. Thereunder prints are arranged alphabetically by printmaker's surname.
Missing Title
Series I. Prints 16 x 20" and smaller
Series II. Prints 16 x 20" to 30 x 40"
Series III. Prints larger than 30 x 40"
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Additional fine art prints with a subject of New York City can be found in the James Boyd Collection of New York City Etchings (PR 007).
Separated Materials Note
Over time several groups of prints have been removed from this collection and established as discrete collections. These were:
PR 162 Audubon Print Collection
PR 216 Alexander Anderson Print Collection
PR 217 John Hill Print Collection
PR 220 William James Bennett Print Collection
PR 221 Asher B. Durand Print Collection
PR 224 Peter Maverick Print File
PR 225 Anthony Imbert Print Collection
PR 226 James King Print Collection
PR 227 Saint-Memin Print Collection
PR 230 Currier and Ives Print File
PR 388 Print Club of New York Presentation Prints
In December 2017, a new collection was formed: New-York Historical Society Collection of Prints from the Works Progress Administration, Federal Art Project (PR 345). Several works were removed from the Printmaker's File at that time and transfered to PR 345. WPA-related prints by the following artists were moved: Lou Barlow, Sarah Berman, Hugh Botts, David Burke, Mabel Dwight (Buried Treasure), Eli Jacoby (Tattoo Artist), and Ann Nooney.
Adirondack Mountains (N.Y.); Brooklyn Bridge (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; Central Park (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) -- Description and travel; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; New York (State) -- Description and travel; Savannah (Ga.); United States -- Description and travel; Aquatints (prints); Chromolithographs; Drypoints; Engravings; Etchings (prints); Linocuts; Lithographs.; Mezzotints (prints); Prints (visual works).; Woodcuts (prints); Boston Massacre, 1770; Skyscrapers -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works; Subways -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works; Bufford's Lithographs (New York); Burgis, William, fl. 1722-1736; Davis, Alexander Jackson, 1803-1892; Doolittle, Amos, 1754-1832; H.F. Sumner & Co.; Hoff, Henry; Milbert, Jacques Gérard, 1766-1840; New York Stock Exchange -- Pictorial works; Revere, Paul, 1735-1818; Sandby, Paul, 1731-1809; Whistler, James McNeill, 1834-1903; Woodcut Society (Kansas City, Mo.); Woolworth Building (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; Flatiron Building (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; Wolchonok, Lou; White, Charles Henry, b. 1878; Wallace, William Henry, 1838-1929; Trueblood, Emily; Sloat, Richard, 1945-; Schutz, Anton Joseph Freidrich, 1894-1977; Roth, Ernest David, $d 1879-1964; Reisman, Philip, 1904-; Parish, Betty Waldo, 1910-1986; Mielatz, Charles Frederick William, 1860-; Meyerowitz, William, 1887-1981; Lowell, Nat; Hunter, F. Leo; Hewitt, Edward Shepard, b. 1877; Berdanier, Paul F. (Paul Frederick), b. 1879.; Arms, John Taylor, 1887-1953; Briem, Gottlob L; Cohen, Arthur (Arthur Morris), 1928-; Dehmann, Karl; Eichenberg, Fritz, 1901-1990; Falconer, John Mackie, 1820-1903; Fernbach, Agnes; Flanagan, Albert; Gayler, Julius F.; Golinkin, Joseph W. $q (Joseph Webster), $d 1896-; Grooms, Red; Hassam, Childe, 1859-1935; Haas, Richard, 1936-
- Series I: Prints 16 x 20" and smaller, 111472
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. Prints 16 x 20" and smaller, is arranged alphabetically by artist or printmaker's surname. These prints are housed in boxes. Not all prints are item-level described here. See the box listing for a complete list of all printmakers.
  The [Views of the Adirondack Mountain Region], lithographed by John Henry Bufford and published by Bufford's Lithography were commissioned to illustrate the New York State Assembly Document no. 200 which was written in 1837 by several geologists after an expedition to the Adirondack region; here the term "Adirondacks" was first used. These prints are thus notable in that they are the first to show views of the Adirondacks under that name. The complete set of ten lithographed views and five engraved maps was issued separately from the Document in paper covers. Some prints are after painter Charles Cromwell Ingham
  "View of Fort George" (1730-1731), attributed to William Burgis, is the first known engraved view of New York City from the west and the first mezzotint view of the city. This is a unique print, and is enclosed in an eighteenth-century, but not original, frame. John Carwitham's "View of Fort George with the City of New York from the S.W.," itself an early and important view of New York, is based on Burgis' view.
  The illustrated broadside, with a woodcut by S. Burnet of the horse Grand Seignior, is considered to be an early image of the first Arabian horse to be brought to New York. The broadside was published in March of 1805.
  Four hand-colored aquatints are from a drawing book printed and sold by William Charles, of Philadelphia, in 1815. The vignettes show a country cottage, a stone bridge, a country church, and an old mill. Each print has the name "Henry H. Krebs" inscribed along the top.
  George Ellis, a Philadelphia engraver, completed "The Peaceable Kingdom at the Branch," a popular view after Richard Westall, at only age sixteen.
  Henry Hoff, a lithographer and publisher, issued twenty "Views of New-York" in 1850. The colored lithographs were mounted onto decorative cards with a gold border and lettering. Eighteen of these views can be found here.
  Jacques-Gerard Milbert was a French naturalist and artist who traveled in the eastern United States from 1815-1823. Upon his return to France, he issued a portfolio, "A Series of Picturesque Views in North America, by J. Milbert, Corresponding member to the French Museum of natural history and several other scientific establishments, Paris, 1825." [from inscription on cover.] A complete set of the fourteen lithographs is rare; thirteen views and an original paper wrapper are held in this File. Several years later Milbert published more prints of America in a bound portfolio with two separate volumes of text; "Itineraire pittoresque du fleuve Hudson et des Parties laterals. L'amerique du nord." Titles on the prints, which were lithographed after drawings by Milbert, were rendered in French, English, Latin, and German. Fifty-three plates were issued; twelve can be found here. A version of Plate 40, without letters, was lithographed in New York in ca. 1821-1822 by Barnet & Doolittle, the first lithography firm in the United States.
  Paul Revere's print of the Boston Massacre, "The Bloody Massacre Perpetrated in King Street.. ." is one of the most famous American historical prints. He issued his print less than a month after the massacre, and it proved to be an important piece of visual propaganda for colonial Americans.
  Joseph Raskin's etchings show buildings at Harvard University, Princeton University, Amherst College, Williams College, Princeton University, and the University of Virginia.
  Caleb Ward's "View of the Spot where Gen. Hamilton fell at Weehawk" is extremely rare. It was first issued just after the erection of the monument in 1806, and then again in ca. 1830.
  James Abbott McNeill Whistler's "Twelve Etchings from Nature," are predominantly views of the French countryside, but also include several urban scenes.
  The Woodcut Society, an organization for print enthusiasts that existed between 1932 and 1952, published two prints a year. Eight of these prints can be found in this File.
  Prints are filed alphabetically in boxes. Prints by Henry Hoff, Jacques Gerard Milbert, and those published by the Woodcut Society are housed in their own boxes.
  - Abel, Carl, 111733
    - Four line engravings of a farmhouse, meadow, and brook, undated; 111735 (Box "A", Folder unknown container)
    - Two line engravings of the ocean, undated; 111734 (Box "A", Folder unknown container)
  - Adams, Wayman (1883-1959), 111731
    - [African American woman and two children], undated; 111732 (Box "A", Folder unknown container)
      Scope and Contents
      lithograph
  - Aikman, Walter M. (1857-1939?), 20972
    - [W. & J. Sloane storefront, 245 Broadway at Murray [1843-1856], 1919; 20973 (Box "A", Folder unknown container)
  - Anderson, Clarence William (1891-1971), 20970
    - The Last Stand [horse and carriage at Central Park], undated; 20971 (Box "A", Folder unknown container)
  - Arms, John Taylor (1887-1953), 20968
    - Sketch, Grolier Club Library, Demonstration Print [2 copies], 1941; 20969 (Box "A", Folder unknown container)
  - Bacher, Otto (1856-1909), 20966
    - [Central Park; model boats on lake], 1888; 20967 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
  - Baker, John (fl. 1832-1835), 111729
    - "The Return", undated; 111730 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
      engraving
  - Beal, Gifford (1866-1951), 111769
    - [Chinese restaurant], undated; 111771 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - [Gathering Brush], undated; 111772 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - [Winter, Central Park], undated; 111773 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - [East River Morning], undated; 111775 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - [View of Central Park], undated; 111777 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - Lake, Central Park, undated; 111778 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
  - Beal, Reynolds (1866-1951), 20962
    - Brooklyn Bridge, 1929; 20963 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
  - Berdanier, Paul F., Sr. (1879-1947), 20957
    - [Christopher Street, looking west] (5/7), undated; 20961 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - East River Nocturne, undated; 20960 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - Lower East Side- New York, undated; 20959 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - New York East Side, undated; 20958 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
  - Bianco, Pamela (b. 1906), 111727
    - [Geraniums], ca. 1930-1939; 111728 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
      General note
  - Bishop, Isabel (1902-1988), 20955
    - [Three men on Fourteenth Street], 1986; 20956 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
  - Blamney, Helen Forley (1849-1902), 111781
    - [Lake in moonlight], 1889; 111782 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
  - Briem, Gottlob L. (1899-1972), 20951
    - The Chrysler Building, New York City, N.Y., undated; 20954 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
      See: Series II
    - 6th Avenue N.Y.C., N.Y., undated; 20953 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - Power, Washington Bridge, undated; 20952 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
  - Browne, Syd J. (1907-91), 20947
    - Riverside Viaduct, 1939; 20950 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - Sutton Place, East River (imp. 4), 1938; 20949 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - Sutton Place, N.Y., 1938; 20948 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - "The Palisades", 1939; 111724 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
      engraving, impression 2 of 50
  - Brussel-Smith, Bernard (1914-1989), 20945
    - No. 8 Bowery (23/50), 1947; 20946 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
      wood engraving
  - Bry, Edith (1898-1991), 111718
    - "Dusk", undated; 111722 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
      lithograph, 2 copies, impressions 20 and 24 of 25
    - "Aged", undated; 111721 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
      lithograph, impression 3 of 20
    - [Two nuns], undated; 111720 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
      lithograph, impression 2 of 20
    - "Devout", undated; 111719 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
      Scope and Contents Note
      lithograph. See also Series II.
    - Cabbies, [1935]; 20944 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - Lunch at the Zoo (1/25), [1935]; 20943 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
  - Bufford, John Henry (1810-1870), 111701
    Includes [Views of the Adirondack Mountain Region], (New York: 1838)
    - "Rossie Lead Vein", 111717 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - "View of the Indian Pass", 111716 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
      after Charles Cromwell Ingham, 1796-1863
    - "View of the Adirondack Mountains Mt. Marcy Mt. McIntyre", 111715 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
      after Ebenezer Emmons, 1799-1863
    - "Trap Dyck, at Avalanche Lake", 111714 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
      after Charles Cromwell Ingham
    - "View at Lake Colden", 111713 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - "Distant View of Mt. Marcy", 111712 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
      after Ebenexer Emmons
    - "View of Mt. McMartin", 111711 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - "View of the Indian Pass, from Lake Henderson", 111710 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - "View of the Dial Mountain", 111709 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - "Map of the Tertiary of Essex Co.", 111708 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
      engraved by George W. Merchant, 1789 or 90-1843
    - "Mining District of Rossie", 111707 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
      engraved by George W. Merchant
    - "Falls of the Genesee", 111706 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - "Section from the Mouth of the Genesee River to Instantur Penn", 111705 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - "Geology of the Genesee River", 111704 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - "Vertical Section showing Relative Thickness of the Different Rocks", 111703 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
  - Burgis, William (fl. 1716-1731), 111698
    - "View of Fort George", 1730-1731; 111700 (Box Burgis, William, Folder unknown container)
      hand-colored mezzotint
    - "View of the New Dutch Church", 1731; 111699 (Box Burgis, William, Folder unknown container)
      engraving. See also Series III.
  - Burnet, S., 111696
    - "The Celebrated Arabian Horse Grand Seignior", 1805; 111697 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
      broadside illustrated with woodcut, printed by John Tiebout, New York
  - Carwitham, John (fl. 1723-1741), 111694
    - "A View of Fort George with the City of New York from the S. W.,", after 1764; 111695 (Box "C", Folder unknown container)
      hand-colored line engraving, printed for Carrington Bowles, London, [date pictured ca. 1731]
  - Chamberlain, Samuel (1895-1975), 20940 (Box "B", Folder unknown container)
    - Manhattan Twilight (61/100), undated; 20941 (Box "C", Folder unknown container)
  - Charles, William (1776-1820), 111692
    - Four hand-colored aquatint vignettes from a drawing book, [1815]; 111693 (Box "C", Folder unknown container)
  - Church, Frederick Stuart (1842-1924), 111690
    - [Woman with bird], 1887; 111691 (Box "C", Folder unknown container)
  - Cole, Timothy (1852-1931), 111683
    - "Mrs. Graham, [after] Gainsborough", 1930; 111689 (Box "C", Folder unknown container)
      on tissue
    - "Broken pitcher, [after] Greuze", 1907; 111688 (Box "C", Folder unknown container)
    - "Frag. Feliz Ortensio Palavicino by El. Greco, Boston Art Museum", 1930; 111687 (Box "C", Folder unknown container)
    - "Princess Cattaneo by Van Duyck", 1930; 111686 (Box "C", Folder unknown container)
    - [Mona Lisa], 1914; 111685 (Box "C", Folder unknown container)
    - [After Eugene Carriere], 1909; 111684 (Box "C", Folder unknown container)
  - Darley, F. O. C. (Felix Octavus Carr) (1821-1888), 111679
    - Five small vignettes, 111682 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
    - Title plate from Illustrations of the Legend of Sleepy Hollow, 111681 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
    - "Four Seasons", 1869; 111680 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
      foldout from Art Supplement to Appleton's Journal
  - Dehmann, Karl (1886-1974), 20927
    - Giants & Dwarfs, [1915-20]; 20939 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
      drypoint etching
    - Grand Central Terminal, [1915-20]; 20938 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
    - Lower Broadway, [1915-20]; 20937 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
    - Liberty Glances at Manhattan, [1915-20]; 20936 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
    - Netherland, Savoy, Plaza, [1915-20]; 20935 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
    - Penn. R.R. Stn, [1915-20]; 20934 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
    - Pershing Square, [1915-20]; 20933 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
    - St. Paul's Church, [1915-20]; 20932 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
    - Stock Exchange, [1915-20]; 20931 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
    - Temples Old & New, [1915-20]; 20930 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
    - Towers of Gold, [1915-20]; 20929 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
    - The Way Called Broad, [1915-20]; 20928 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
  - Deville, Henri (French 1871-?; active in US 1902-14), 20925
    - City Hall Park (3/25), 1911; 20926 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
  - De Witt, Gerard, 20922
    - [Grand Central Station], undated; 20924 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
    - Pennsylvania Station], undated; 20923 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
  - Di Cerbo, Michael (b.1947), 20920
    - Parapets (19/70), 2001; 20921 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
      etching and aquatint
  - Dirnfeld, Frederick A., 111785
    - 11 etchings of Manhattan scenes, undated; 111786 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
  - Dolice, Leon Louie (1892-1960), 20916
    - Chrysler Building, undated; 20919 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
    - The East River N.Y., undated; 20918 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
    - The Little Church Around the Corner, undated; 20917 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
  - Dwight, Mabel (1876-1955), 20914
    - Old Greenwich Village, 1928; 20915 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
      Lithograph, printed by George Miller. See also N-YHS collection of prints from the Works Progress Administration, Federal Arts Project (PR 345) for Mabel Dwight prints.
  - Dwight, Theodore, Jr. (1796-1866), 111677
    - Six lithographs, views of the Hudson River, Catskills, and Hudson River Valley., undated; 111678 (Box "D", Folder unknown container)
      Several copies of each, some hand-colored.
  - Eichenberg, Fritz (1901-1990), 20912
    - Subway, 1934; 20913 (Box "E", Folder unknown container)
      Woodcut. See also N-YHS collection of prints from the Works Progress Administration, Federal Arts Project (PR 345) for an Eichenberg print.
  - Ellis, George B. (fl. 1821-1838), 111675
    - "The Peaceable Kingdom of the Branch", 1819; 111676 (Box "E", Folder unknown container)
      engraving after Richard Westall, 1765-1836
  - Ehrgott, Forbriger & Co. (fl. 1860-1869), 177815 (Box E)
    Acquisition Note
    Purchased from Howard Holzer, 2016
    Biographical/Historical Note
    Ehrgott, Forbriger & Co. was founded in 1856 by Peter E. Ehrgott and Adolphus F.Forbriger in Cincinatti, Ohio. Ehrgott and Forbriger introduced the first steam press west of New York City in 1868. Their lithographic firm published a series of portraits of Civil War military and naval officers. These portraits are notable for the fact that though the face of each individual is accurate and based on a photograph, many share the same, or very similar backgrounds, with identical bodies, horses, landscapes, etc. Seventeen of these Civil War portraits are included in this subseries.